Hi I'm Les Whitley and I would like to take a few moments right now and tell you how to train for the shot put.
The shot put is a very popular olympic event which requires a lot of power and force to overcome the weight and gravity of an object such as the shot put itself.
That requires a lot of explosive power that is developed through strength training, strength training utilizing the lower body as well as the upper body exercises such as the squat, the overhead press or olympic movements such as the clean and jerk or the olympic snatch.
The goal there is to move an object through space as quickly as possible.
The olympic movements are exactly that and train the body to recruit maximal power for a very short period of time to cover a lot of ground in moving weights through space.
The next thing becomes technique.
You can be extremely strong and have poor technique and be a pretty decent shot putter.
You can have great technique and not be very strong and your shot put is not going to go as far.
So it is important to have a good balance of technique as well as strength.
The shot put involves basic aspects of geometry and physics.
Physics in overcoming gravity and utilizing your body to propel an object through space at an appropriate angle where the geometry comes into it.
Ideally between not quite a 90, not quite flat out but somewhere around a 45 degree angle to get the shot put to travel at an appropriate distance to cover maximal ground.
Next becomes position whether you utilize the glide technique where your body is actually traveling through a straight line as you approach the ring, body moving back the shot put is placed back, you are balancing off of one leg.
You are actually traveling in a linear position pushing your body back, rotating through, extending the body and pushing through that arc, maintaining that 45 degree angle as the shot put leaves.
The other is the rotational spin where if you had imagined the circle being here, the body goes into a power position, you actually spin through, block through and accelerate the shot put through.
The basic technique involves tucking under the chin, the arm accelerates through the body rotates through using the leg drive, rotational force of the body.
Block with the arm to cause the opposite side to push through as you drive the object of the shot put through space.